Article starting on page 42.
MCCIA Event Food Safety Summit Puts Technology and Compliance in Focus MCCIA Calls for Stronger Industry–Regulator Collaboration MCCIA’s Food Safety Summit 2026, held in Pune on July 18, brought regulators, food businesses, laboratories, industry associations and food-safety professionals together to discuss regulatory preparedness, technology, traceability, product innovation and emerging risks across India’s food sector.
The Mahratta Chamber of Commerce, Industries and Agriculture (MCCIA) organised Food Safety Summit 2026 with a keynote address, fireside conversation and industry panel covering issues ranging from regulatory compliance and product development to laboratory testing, e-commerce, traceability and organisational food-safety practices.
The discussions highlighted the need for closer coordination among regulators, industry, laboratories, academia and industry Maharashtra FDA Commissioner associations as India’s food economy expands Advocates 360-Degree and new distribution channels emerge.
Regulation Delivering the keynote address, Tukaram Food regulation needs to MCCIA Calls for Mundhe, IAS, Commissioner, Food and Collaborative Approach consider farmers, businesses, Drug Administration (FDA), Government Opening the Summit, Prashant Girbane, consumers and enforcement of Maharashtra, called for a 360-degree Director General, MCCIA, highlighted agencies while balancing approach to food regulation that considers the Chamber’s work in industry advocacy, the perspectives of farmers,
food businesses, consumer protection with capacity building and institution-building.
consumers and enforcement agencies.
He emphasised awareness, training, the realities of agriculture, Drawing on his farming background and handholding and institutional support industry and commerce.
administrative experience across industry, for registered as well as unregistered food taxation and small-scale industry, Mr. Mundhe businesses.
said policy formulation must consider both Anand Chordia, Chairman, Food intended outcomes and possible unintended Processing Committee, MCCIA, called consequences.
He stressed the importance for stronger collaboration among industry, of balancing consumer protection with the regulators, laboratories and academia.
He operational realities of agriculture, industry and also outlined MCCIA’s initiatives in food commerce.
safety, training and innovation and referred In a fireside conversation moderated by to the proposed Food Cluster as a support Smita Murthy, FSSC India Representative, Mr. ecosystem that could provide MSMEs with Mundhe discussed the need for continuing access to knowledge, technology, testing and dialogue between regulators and the food handholding.
42 | SAMPADA | august 2026
manufacturers, arguing that responsibility for 5 product safety and quality cannot end at the factory gate.
He suggested that manufacturers assess e-commerce partners with the same seriousness applied to suppliers and distributors since consumers continue to associate their Key Takeaways experience with the product brand.
Compliance challenges faced by MSMEs 1.
DESIGN FOR SAFETY were another focus.
Asha Sridhar pointed to Quality and regulatory the gap between understanding regulations and requirements need to enter converting them into operational requirements, product development at the Head, Suhana Pravin Masalewale; Nilesh while Ritesh Madvaiya noted that businesses concept stage rather than after a Amritkar, MD, Envirocare Labs, Mumbai; may have the intent to comply but lack product is ready.
Ritesh Madvaiya, VP and Head of Quality, Parle clarity on how requirements apply to specific 2.
USE LAB DATA Products; Saili Jahagirdar, Chapter Head, Pune, products, processes or facilities.
The discussion historical laboratory data and NRAI; and Sandhya Khorate, Head R&D/ identified a role for industry associations analytical tools can help identify Associate Director, Tasty Bite Eatables Ltd. such as MCCIA in translating regulations recurring failures, contaminants The panel examined food safety across into practical guidance through training and and emerging risks.
product development, manufacturing, awareness.
3. laboratories, restaurants, supply chains and EXTEND RESPONSIBILITY Traceability Linked to emerging distribution channels.
Asha Sridhar Food-safety oversight Business Efficiency stressed the need to involve quality, regulatory, increasingly needs to cover Traceability emerged as an important compliance, culinary, packaging, branding and e-commerce and quick- operational priority.
Anupama Patil said sales teams from product conception through commerce partners beyond the responsibility for traceability applies to every pre-launch, particularly when products are factory gate.
food business operator, including smaller 4.
intended for export markets.
Sandhya Khorate STRENGTHEN TRACEABILITY enterprises that may rely on basic batch, lot emphasised that ingredients, processes, Even smaller businesses can and product-movement records rather than reproducibility, shelf life and manufacturing maintain basic batch, lot sophisticated digital systems.
consistency must be considered during product and movement records to Ritesh Madvaiya linked stronger development itself.
improve visibility and recall traceability with better inventory management, preparedness.
lower wastage and movement of products Labs, Data and Emerging Risks 5.
through the supply chain within their shelf life.
BUILD CAPABILITY Nilesh Amritkar highlighted the role The concluding discussion focused on Training, regulatory guidance of laboratories beyond regulatory testing, regulatory compliance, food-safety standards, and institutional support pointing to the large volumes of data generated quality-management systems, laboratory can help MSMEs translate through testing and the potential for artificial quality management and organisational culture.
compliance requirements into intelligence to identify patterns in product Nilesh Amritkar, using a “push and pull” day-to-day operations.
failures, contaminants and geographical analogy, said regulation can push businesses sources.
The discussion also stressed the towards higher standards while companies can importance of retaining historical test data and pull their suppliers and supply chains towards industry as new products, technologies, scientifically validating product shelf life.
improved practices.
The Summit concluded e-commerce and quick commerce alter the Emerging contaminants including by highlighting the complementary roles sector.
The discussion also highlighted the need PFAS, ethylene oxide and alkaloids were of regulators, laboratories, manufacturers, for greater awareness and institutional support also discussed.
Anupama Patil explained that restaurants and food-service businesses, for MSMEs
with limited regulatory and regulatory changes draw on surveillance, academia and industry associations in technical resources.
recalls, scientific information and stakeholder strengthening the food-safety ecosystem.
consultations involving food businesses, l Industry Panel Looks laboratories, scientists and academicians.
Beyond Compliance The industry panel, moderated by Smita E-Commerce Extends Murthy,
featured Anupama Patil, Assistant Responsibility Scan the QR code to Commissioner of Food, FDA, Government of Ritesh Madvaiya highlighted the implications listen to the gist of the Maharashtra; Asha Sridhar, Corporate Quality of e-commerce and quick commerce for article.
august 2026 | SAMPADA | 43
This article is from Sampada, published by MCCIA.